Erie Lackawanna Railway Company Records 5013
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Erie Lackawanna Railway Company Records
1903-1966
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Erie Lackawanna Railway Company (EL)
Erie Railroad Company (ERIE)
Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Company
5013
1.5 cubic feet
1.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Reports and publications generated or collected by the Erie Lackawanna Railroad Company. Includes records from both the Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Company and the Erie Railroad, the two predecessor railroad companies that formed the Erie Lackawanna Railroad Company.
5984241
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, April 01, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, April 02, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Erie Lackawanna Railway [EL], known as the Erie Lackawanna Railroad until 1968, was formed from the 1960 merger of the Erie Railroad and the Delaware, Lackawanna & Western Railroad. The two railroads merged because of a loss of income that occurred because of declining passenger traffic, lower freight shipments because of the decline of coal in western Pennsylvania, and the damage caused to track systems by Hurricane Diane in 1956.
The Interstate Commerce Commission approved the merger on September 13, 1960, and on October 17 the Erie Railroad and Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad merged to form the Erie-Lackawanna Railroad. For the previous four years, the two lines had already begun consolidating their assets, particularly their facilities on the Hudson River waterfront and their trackage through southern New York State. After the merger, the EL did manage to regain profitability in the late 1960s.
The Erie Lackawanna Railway, as opposed to "railroad," was formed March 1, 1968 as a subsidiary of the Norfolk and Western Railway [NW], which had purchased the EL. Due to a combination of the continuing decline in railroad traffic, both passenger and freight, and the major losses suffered by the railway during Hurricane Agnes in 1972, the EL was forced to declare bankruptcy. Although the company initially resisted joining the consolidation of eastern rail lines by the federal government, it was eventually forced to change its position due to the fincial burdens caused by the oil shortages of the early 1970s. In 1976, the EL was able to successfully petition the federal governement and join the ConRail system.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1903-1966
Bulk dates: 1909-1956
This collection consists of records from the Erie-Lackawanna Railroad Company. The majority of the records pre-date the founding of the EL, and as such offer more information on the Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Company and the Erie Railroad. Of particular interest are the numerous personnel directories for both railroad companies, which contain the names of employees, their positions, their addresses and telephone numbers. Guides to stations served by both railroad systems provide a comprehensive view of the regions served by both railroads. Additionally, the annual reports include promotional pictures, some of which document damage to the systems, locomotives used by both systems, and company headquarters.
There is also documentation concerning the regulation of the railroad industry during World War II by the War Manpower Commission. Additionally, there are records addressing general regulations on the railroads in areas such as wages and interstate commerce. Finally, there are records of meetings with the United States Railroad Labor Boards regarding the national agreements regarding rules and working conditions.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5992 AV: "A Stitch in Time: The History and Future of the Garment Industry Union" Workshop Audio-Visual Materials /4229 AV: Maurice Neufeld "The Future of the American Labor Movement" Audio-Visual Materials 5158m: New York State Window Glass Manufacturers' Mutual Benefit Association and the Window Glass Manufacturers' Beneficial Association Agreement 6220: U.S. Commission on the Future of Worker-Management Relations (Dunlop Commission) Documents 6055: UTU Additional Collective Bargaining Agreements 6023: UTU Additional Records 5139 AV: UTU Audio-Visual Material 5164: UTU Canada Records 5196: UTU Ladies' Auxiliary Iowa Joint Board Minutes 5139 MB: UTU Memorabilia 5622: UTU New York State Legislative Board Selected Files 5711: UTU New York State Legislative Director Files 5139 P: UTU Photographs 5139: UTU Records 5589: UTU Vice-President's Office George W. Legg Subject Files 5501 AV: UTU. Young Leadership Conference Audiorecordings
Railroads; Erie-Lackawanna Railroad Company. Archives.; Erie Lackawanna Railway Company.; Erie Railroad Company; ConRail
5984241
- War Manpower Commission Stabilization Plans, U.S. Railroad Retirement Board [folder 1 of 3], 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- War Manpower Commission Stabilization Plans, U.S. Railroad Retirement Board. [folder 2 of 3], 1943; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
- War Manpower Commission Stabilization Plans, U.S. Railroad Retirement Board [folder 3 of 3], 1943; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Erie Railroad Company Reorganization, Interstate Commerce Commission, 1941; Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
- American Railroads Their Growth and Development, Association of American Railroads, 1956; Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Rules for Reporting Information on Railroad Employees with A Classification and Index of Steam Railroad Occupations, 1921; Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Scope and Contents
  United States Railroad Labor Board. Wage Series, Report No. 2
- Erie Railroad Company Hand Book and Yearbook, 1922-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: Erie Railroad Company New York Terminal Region Handbook, 1922; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Handbook of Special Instructions and Condensed Bulletins, in effect February 1, 1922. Signature of A. J. Schilling on cover.
    Format: Pamphlet.
  - Item 2: Yearbook of Railroad Information, 1956 Edition, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 7)
- List of Station Names and Numbers, Erie Railroad Company, Baggage Department, 1916; Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
  May 1 1916. Signature of A. J. Schilling on cover. Booklet is annotated with updates to station names and notes on agents at stations.
- Lackawanna Railroad List of Officers, Station Agents, Etc., 1908; Publication (Box 2, Folder 1)
  October 1st, 1908.
- Lackawanna Railroad pamphlets, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: The Delaware Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co. Pamphlet, 1934; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment and Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; First Aid to the Injured; Residence Address and Telephone Directory. June 1, 1934
  - Item 2: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co. Pamphlet, 1935; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 2)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment and Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; First Aid to the Injured; Residence Address and Telephone Directory. July 1, 1935
- Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad: List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc., 1909; Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
  April 1st, 1909
- Lackawanna Railroad pamphlets, 1913-1916 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1916; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 4)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. April 1916.
  - Item 2: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1915; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 4)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. April 1915.
  - Item 3: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1913; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 4)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. August 1913.
  - Item 4: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1913; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 4)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. April 1913
- Lackawanna Railroad pamphlets, 1917-1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1917; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 5)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. April 1917
  - Item 2: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1920; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 5)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. June 1920.
  - Item 3: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1922; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 5)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. March 1922.
  - Item 4: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1926; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 5)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. July 1926
- Lackawanna Railroad pamphlets, 1916-1931 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1916; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 6)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. October 1916.
  - Item 2: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1924; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 6)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. March 1924
  - Item 3: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1926; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 6)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. July 1926.
  - Item 4: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1929; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 6)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. October 1929
  - Item 5: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1931; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 6)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. July 1, 1931.
- Lackawanna railroad pamphlets, 1909-1912 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1909; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 7)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. October 1, 1909
  - Item 2: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1910; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 7)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. April 1, 1910
  - Item 3: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1910; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 7)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. October 1, 1910.
  - Item 4: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1911; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 7)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. April 1, 1911
  - Item 5: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1911; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 7)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. October 1, 1911.
  - Item 6: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1912; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 7)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. June 1, 1912.
  - Item 7: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1912; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 7)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc.; Instructions for Railway Mail; Telephone Directory; First Aid to the Injured. October 1912.
- Statements Made by the Association of Railway Executives, Conference Committee of Managers before the United States Railroad Labor Board, 1921; Publication (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Before the United States Railroad Labor Board, Chicago, Il., January 10-18, 1921. Also included: Insert to the volume, Closing Statements of the Association of Railway Executives, Conference Committee of Managers before the United States Railroad Labor Board. January 27, 1921.
- Inquiry of The Attorney General's Committee On Administrative Procedure, 1939; Publication (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Relating to the National Railroad Adjustment Board and Historical Background And Growth Of Machinery set up for the Handling Of Railroad Labor Disputes 1888-1940. Compiled by Harry E. Jones, Executive Secretary for the National Railroad Adjustment Board.
- Lackawanna Railroad pamphlets, 1903-1908 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1903; Pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 3)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc. January 1, 1903.
  - Item 2: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1904; Pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 3)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc. January 1, 1904
  - Item 3: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1905; Pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 3)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc. January 1, 1905.
  - Item 4: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1906; Pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 3)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc. April 1, 1906.
  - Item 5: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1906; Pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 3)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc. October 1, 1906.
  - Item 6: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1907; Pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 3)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc. October 1, 1907.
  - Item 7: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1907; Pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 3)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc. April 1, 1907.
  - Item 8: The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 1908; Pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 3)
    List of Officers, Agents, Stations, Equipment, Facilities, Etc. April 1, 1908.
- The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Co., 105th Annual Report for 1956, 1957; Publication (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Includes notes for shareholder meeting, March 20, 1957.
- Annual Report, Erie Lackawanna Railroad Company, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  For fiscal years 1964 and 1965.
  - Item 1: Annual Report 1964, Publication (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Author: Erie Lackawanna Railroad Company
    Format: Publication
    Language: English.
  - Item 2: Annual Report 1965, Publication (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Pamphlets and Newsletters re Interstate Commerce and Regulation, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: The Great U.S. Freight Cartel, 1957; Publication (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Author: Gilbert Burck
  - Item 2: Revision of Federal Transportation Policy, 1955; Publication (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Notes: April 1955
  - Item 3: Congressional Record Let's Keep the Railroads Ready, 1956; Publication (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Notes: March 23, 1956
  - Item 4: Memorandum on Changes in Minimum-Maximum Rate Controls, 1955; Publication (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Item 5: The Right to Compete Cornerstone of Modern Transportation Regulation, 1956; Publication (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Author: William T. Faricy
  - Item 6: Questions and Answers from Transcript, 1956; Publication (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Author: Eastern Railroad Presidents Conference
  - Item 7: The 25 Billion Question, Publication (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Author: David I. Mackie
- Pamphlets and newsletters re Railroad Community Committee, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: Railroad Community Committee Activities Make News, 1956; Publication (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Item 2: Community Committee Digest, 1957; Publication (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Item 3: Grass Roots Work Bears Fruit, 1956; Publication (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Notes: October 29, 1956
- Super-Railroads for a Dynamic American Economy, John Walker Barriger, 1956; Publication (Box 3, Folder 8)
- The Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad Company Board of Managers Inspection Trip, 1956; Publication (Box 3, Folder 9)
  October 18-19, 1956. Contains information on track grades, the 104th Annual Report for FY1955 with pictures of the damage done by Hurricane Diane to track system, and train time table for 1956.